A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Tehran Office Program Files FA1534
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Tehran Office Program Files
1952-1964
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1534
4 Cubic Feet 9 Hollinger boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the program files of the Ford Foundation field office in Tehran, Iran. These files concern Foundation fellowships related to Iran and Iranian awardees as well as the two main focus areas of the Tehran Office's program activity: educational development and rural village development. Records are organized into three individual series based on these three different subjects. With materials spanning from 1952 to 1964, the collection documents the entire history of Ford Foundation support to Iran as conducted through the Tehran Field Office which was established in 1959. Prior to 1959, programming for Iran was run out of the Ford Foundation's Beirut, Lebanon Office.
Correspondence, memos, drafts, notes, and reports within the collection were created by the Tehran Office program specialist/consultant staff (Paul Maris – Agricultural Development, Arthur Lewis – Education, Howard Bertsch – Rural Development) and representatives (Bertsch and Rey Hill). These records document communications between the Tehran staff and its supervising office, the Office of the Near East Representative in Beirut, Lebanon, other parts of the Ford Foundation, Iranian Government officials and staff, grantees like the Near East Foundation, collaborating organizations, and individual fellows. They also regard meetings between Foundation staff and Iranian Government officials, grant project proposals, approvals, progress, and close outs, coordination of travel awards for Iranian awardees, and assistance to Foundation fellows conducting research in Iran. In addition to the aforementioned material formats, there are some photographs and publications in the collection.
Materials in the collection originate from two different sets of records transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center. Files in Series 1. Fellowships and Series 3. Rural village development programs originated from an accession of program strategy records, and files in Series 2. Education grants originated from an accession of grant records. The materials' original containers and content indicated that the records were initially all organized together and were thus processed as one Tehran Office Program Files collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as parts of Accession 2019:046 Ford Foundation records, Program Strategy records and Accession 2019:049 Ford Foundation records, Grant records.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of three series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Fellowships, 1953-1964
Series 2. Education grants, 1955-1964
Series 3. Rural village development programs, 1952-1964
Biographical / Historical
Between 1952 and 1964, the Ford Foundation provided grant support to a number of different rural development and educational development projects in Iran. Programming in Iran was overseen by the Foundation's Office of the Near East Representative in Beirut, Lebanon, and in 1959, the Tehran, Iran Field Office was established. Work in the Tehran Office was conducted by a small number of program specialists/consultants and representative staff members. Over the years, program specialist/consultant staff included Paul Maris as an Agricultural Consultant, Arthur Lewis as a Program Specialist in Education, and Howard Bertsch as a Rural Development Consultant. Bertsch later served as a Consultant-Representative before Rey Hill succeeded him as Representative for Iran.
Ford issued grants directly to Iranian Government branches and organizations as well as to organizations providing assistance to Iran like the Near East Foundation. Rural development grants chiefly concerned agricultural credit cooperatives, village worker training programs, and projects that involved women in village development. Educational development grants chiefly concerned teacher training and curriculum development. The Tehran Office also coordinated Travel and Study Awards Program grants and other fellowships to individuals from Iran with the Beirut Office and assisted Ford fellows conducting research in Iran.
Ford Foundation programming in Iran was discontinued in 1964 as per the recommendations of Rey Hill.
Ford Foundation; Iran; Rural development -- Iran; Agricultural development projects -- Iran; Education and state -- Iran; Curriculum planning -- Iran; Rural credit
- Fellowships, 1953-1964; 1; 1.18 Cubic Feet About 2.5 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The series mostly contains files regarding Ford Foundation fellowships granted to Iranian citizens as well as Ford fellows conducting research in Iran. Iranians granted Travel and Study Awards Program grants and special fellowships by the Foundation were primarily interested in agricultural and rural development. Some of the correspondence regarding the Travel and Study Awards Program grantees discusses the Foundation's emphasis on grantees returning to Iran in order to apply their acquired knowledge and skills to the improvement of their home country. Other documents in the series show how the Tehran Office assisted Ford fellows journeying to and staying in Iran for the purpose of their research.
  The series also contains a small amount of material regarding the Ford Foundation's support of agricultural and rural development programs in Burma. This material is comprised of lists of Foundation supported projects in Burma, reports, publications, and correspondence. It is unclear why these documents were stored with the Tehran Office records when they seem to have been created by the Foundation's office in Rangoon, Burma. One connection may be the two offices' shared interest in rural development programming.
  - Travel and Study Awards Program, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Awards:
    Kayvan Najm-Abadi
    Ghassem Touyserkani
    Mohamad Sam
    Karim Fatemi
    Iraj Valipour
    Miscellaneous Travel and Study Grants
  - Mostofi, Khosrow - Agricultural Project for Iran, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sharify, Nasir - Special Fellowship, 1953-1958; File contains still image. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Image in the file is a photograph of Nasir Sharify that was attached to a fellowship application.
  - Ford Foundation Fellows, 1955-1962; File contains a still image. (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    The image in the file is a photograph of Kokab Moarefi that was attached to an application.
  - Overseas Development Training Associates, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Travel and Study Awards Program - Hossein Mahdavi, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Arasteh, Reza, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Omid Shafa, Farangis - Request for Special Fellowship, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Jazayery, Mohammad Ali, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hashimzade Fallah, Jalil - Regarding citrus studies in the United States, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mahmoudi, Jalil - Land tenure reform in Iran, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mossaed, Houshang - Special Fellowship, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fulbright grantees, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Travel and Study Awards Program - University of Shiraz, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Institute of International Education (IIE) - Public Service Fellowships, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Travel and Study Awards Program - Manuchehr Afzal, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Travel and Study Awards Program - Manuchehr Safa-Isfahani, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ford Foundation supported programs - Fellowships, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Reports regarding education and rural development, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Land nationalization and cooperative farming in Burma, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Education in Asia, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Agricultural projects in Burma, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - Travel and Study Awards Program - Ataollah Motadel, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ford Foundation in Burma, 1953-1963 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
- Education grants, 1955-1964; 2; 1.41 Cubic Feet About 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Series contains files regarding grants that the Ford Foundation provided for educational development in Iran. These grants appear to have primarily focused on teacher training and recruitment and curriculum development. Correspondence, drafts, reports, planning materials, financial statements, and photographs document the Foundation's grant support to the National Teachers' College for the purpose of teacher training and recruitment. The files concerning those grants also include materials that discuss the eventual abolishment of the National Teachers' College due to the belief that it did not serve the Iranian Government's needs. Other files in the series regard the Foundation's assistance to the Iranian Government's Ministry of Education on curriculum development for various academic subjects at different educational levels. Some of the correspondence in these files discuss reorganization within the Ministry and potential internal conflict.
  The series also holds some files that regard Foundation grants for the production of educational materials like a Persian language dictionary.
  - Science Teaching in the Middle East - Consultant on science education to the Ministry of Education, Project No. 61-371, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Franklin Publications - Persian dictionary, Project No. 61-4, 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Agricultural school at Shiraz University, 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - National Teachers' College - Teacher-librarian training program, Project No. 60-226, 1960-1963; File contains a set of still images. Photographs have descriptive captions on their backs. (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
    The photographs in the file regard the teacher-librarian training program at the National Teachers' College in Tehran, Iran. They document instructive sessions that were part of the course as well as the work of the apprenticeship teams that were assigned to different school libraries. Photograph captions provide information about the state of school libraries in Iran as well as the teacher-librarian training program. All of the photographs appear to have been created in 1960.
  - National Teachers' College - Recruitment of teachers, Project No. 60-60, 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Improvement of science education - Consultant on science education to the Ministry of Education, Project No. 61-371, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Training of curriculum development specialists, Project No. 61-202, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - National Teachers' College visits, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - National Teachers' College - Administration and guidance training, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - National Teachers' College - Conferences with Manuchehr Taslimi, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Ministry of Education - Secondary Mathematics Committee, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - National Teachers' College - Elementary education, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Ministry of Education - Social studies, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Ministry of Education - Organization for curriculum development, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Ministry of Education - Summer-in-Service Training Course, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Ministry of Education - Science, first cycle, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Ministry of Education - Supervision program, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Ministry of Education - National Science Teachers Association, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Ministry of Education - Science teaching, Travel and Study Awards Program grant, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Ministry of Education - Elementary science curriculum, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Ministry of Education - Persian literature, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Ministry of Education - Elementary health curriculum, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Ministry of Education - Conferences with Karim Fatemi, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Ministry of Education - Administrative organization, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Ministry of Education - Home economics, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Isfahan Conference on Secondary Education, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Iran Commission on Teacher Education, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Possible educational projects in Iran, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Royal Iranian Commission on Education, 1957-1961 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - National University for Teacher Education - Institute of Education and Graduate Studies, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Foshay, Arthur Wells correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Education research center, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Franklin Press - General, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Franklin Press - Reading and language arts, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Franklin Press - Science, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 67)
- Rural village development programs, 1952-1964; 3; 1.41 Cubic Feet About 2.5 LGL and 1 Half-LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Series contains files regarding the Ford Foundation's support of rural village development programs in Iran. The Foundation issued grants directly to the Iranian Government as well as to foreign organizations providing support to Iran like the Near East Foundation. Some files within the series document how over the course of the Tehran Office's history, the Ford Foundation sought to shift the focus of some of its activities in Iran in order to encourage the institutionalization of rural development programs by the Iranian Government and lessen Iran's dependency on foreign aid for programs like rural credit cooperatives. In addition to containing records concerning rural credit cooperatives, the series also holds materials that regard village worker training programs and projects that involved rural Iranian women in village development.
  - John McCauley - Cooperatives in Iran, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Rural credit program, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Near East Foundation - Agricultural credit program, Project No. 54-45, 1953-1958 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Cooperatives - General, 1953-1962 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Cooperative - Varamin, Iran, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Cooperative - Pishva, Iran, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Agricultural credit program, 1953-1964 (Box 7, Folder 74-76)
  - Cooperative - Jajerud, Iran, 1954-1960 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Rural Credit Seminar on Cooperative Agricultural Credit in Iran, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Agricultural Bank of Iran - Agricultural credit cooperatives, 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Near East Foundation - Village Training School, Varamin, Iran, Project No. 54-2, 1952-1957 (Box 8, Folder 80-82)
  - Asadollah Alam speeches - Tehran University lecture series "Agrarian Reform: Its World Wide and Domestic Implications", undated (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Agricultural Bank of Iran Advisory Board, 1954-1959 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Agricultural credit program, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Program for village women, Project No. 55-62 - Najmeh Najafi, 1954-1958 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Near East Foundation - Program for village women, Project No. 55-62, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Government of Iran - Village development block program, Project No. 55-77, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 88-89)